Hello, welcome. It's May 21st, 2025.
We're in active inference guest stream
107.1 with David Benramo. The need for a
common language to unite levels of
explanation in mental health, the
potential of computational psychiatry.
So, thank you for coming, David. looking
forward to the presentation and to
anyone's questions in the live chat. So,
thank you to you. Perfect. Thank you so
much. It's a pleasure to be here. Um I
don't think I've done a live stream
before, so this is a new new experience
for me. Uh looking forward to any
questions that come from the audience.
Um so today I'll be uh talking uh a
little bit about some work we've been
doing. um much of which is is relevant
either directly involving or or
peripherally involving active inference
um around um uh levels of explanation in
in mental health research and um uh and
some new and more recent uh theoretical
work that we've done in in incorporating
a effective states uh into understanding
um things like uh psychosis development
which is a particular interest of mine.
I am a psychiatrist um at um the Douglas
Mental Health University University
Institute which is a mental health
hospital in Montreal, Canada. Um I did a
master's degree with Carl Fristen um at
UCL where we did some some work that
I'll be talking about today on modeling
hallucinations. Um I have a lab at
McGill and I also happen to be uh the
chief science officer of a mental health
company which not really relevant to the
the talk today. It's not active
inference focused at all. Um so just uh
keep in mind uh the uh the disclaimer.
Um so my my journey uh to towards active
inference and towards computational
psychiatry uh in general really was uh
motivated by this difficulty I had as a
medical student as a premedical student
with um the idea that everything seemed
to be about cutting things into from
bigger boxes into smaller boxes. And you
know it's nice to know how many boxes
you you have to deal with but that
doesn't necessarily tell you anything
about what the boxes are actually doing.
Um so you know if you start with humans
uh we can split those into individuals
and societies and then individuals have
a bunch of things that are phenomena and
then those phenomena um we think you
know are are rooted in the brain and
then the brain has regions and then
those light up with different tasks and
what have you um on fMRI and other
things and then those regions have
circuits and then those circuits have
neurons and astroytes and ga and etc and
those have genes which are regulated by
uh by genetic regulators, etc. And so it
all just kind of felt like we were just
breaking things into smaller boxes. And
this is not a dig against a reductionist
approach at all. Um it just didn't feel
like we were quite getting at mechanism.
Um and I always wondered, you know, how
does all this work? What is the
mechanism? What are we actually trying
to achieve? What is the what is the
thing that is being computed? um you
know and of course for all those of you
who uh are interested in in
computational work this is this is by no
means
a an un foreign concept but since I'm
sure many people listening aren't
necessarily thinking about this from a
medical or mental health standpoint um I
just sort of wanted to give you an
insight into how how I think about this
and the utility of computational
psychiatry. So um the way I see it is
that it's using new and old
computational techniques to understand
the healthy and pathological mind or the
environment. no reason why we can't use
it to explain the environment and it
comprised of me different methods that
focus on answering different questions.
What is thought and behavior which we
think is the manipulation of information
um and what answers are useful um and
those are the ones that uh can provide
predictive tools for clinical
preventative use. Sometimes the useful
answers are not the um the ones that
teach us anything about the brain and
vice versa. So we'll be focusing today
mostly on the what is thought and
behavior piece. the predictive stuff is
uh I have another talk for that not
really super relevance to to active
inference per se um you know but it gave
us these two camps of computational
psychiatry the modelers which is where
I'll be focusing most of my focus today
and then the predictors which build
models that are I say useful as a
facicious way um of of indicating that
sometimes the models that we build for
prediction are very helpful we don't
necessarily learn anything from them but
they give us something useful um and
sometimes you have to make that choice
between utility and uh and and mechanis
mechanistic insight. Uh though obviously
with more and more technical um progress
the the the distance between those two
camps is being
reduced. Um so we're going to be
focusing really on model models of
psychosis development from individual
patient level to the social level. And
um psychosis is something I've always
been uh fascinated by uh clinically um
and sort of epistemologically. How does
one generate um uh an understanding of
uh phenomena and and beliefs that that
aren't really there? Um what is the what
is the um the uh the the understanding
of how we can have a base optimal agent
the human brain that is generating
something that seems from the outside
perspective to to not be optimal.
Obviously of course it is but uh for for
complex and interesting
reasons. Um so we built uh in my
master's degree um with Carl a
computational model of auditory
hallucinations and this was because uh
schizophrenia is is a common and
devastating condition and about 70% of
people with schizophrenia will have
auditory
hallucinations. Um we often find
ourselves at a therapeutic deadlock
because likely of poor mechanistic
understanding. We don't really know how
uh the brain is generating uh psychotic
symptoms and so we uh don't really have
any new ideas about treatment. the first
new drug for schizophrenia um RXT which
came out recently. Um, I went to a talk
recently and the thing they were all
interested in was how do we relate this
back to to the dopamine story which has
been very influential for many years
obviously and I went up to the speaker
after it. I said, "Isn't it a shame that
you have a drug with a completely new
mechanism of action and you feel the
need to relate it back to dopamine? Is
it not possible that there might be
other mechanisms at play here that might
be interesting or novel or useful? We
don't have to always have the same
answer." Um because having the same
answer all the time is what's led us to
having a therapeutic deadlock. Um not to
say the dopamine isn't important. It is.
But there's there's possibly and likely
more to the story than
that. Um they have a rich and rich and
complex phenomenology that presents
specific targets for modeling which is
which is always nice to have if you have
phenomenology that you can reproduce in
your models. So we decided to use active
inference. Um I have a slide here on
what is active inference which uh I'm
assuming for this population I do not
have to go through. So I'm going to go
through it extraordinarily quickly just
because it's on my slide list but I'm
not going to I'm going to assume this is
not news to anybody. Um so Beijian
theory we seek to minimize uncertainty
surprise or free energy about causes
sensations. We act to do this. Uh it can
be formulated as exploration
exploitation trade-off. Um, and we
build, it assumes that we build models
of the world and act to maximize the
accuracy of this model while minimizing
complexity. And if you're in a dark room
and you see scary yellow eyes, you will
act to produce more information to
better understand the causes of your
sensations, which in this case was a
harmless kitty, but could not have been
a harmless kitty. And therefore, we
acted to um to get ourselves more
information so that we could reduce
uncertainty. I'm assuming this is not a
surprise to anybody. So, I'm just going
to move on. Um, so to the fun stuff. So,
uh, how might hallucinations occur in a
base optimal context? Um, you know, the,
uh, the idea really was we've got our
priors, our likelihoods, and our
posterior. Our posterior is where the
percept is happening in our
conceptualization. We have, um, a state
that we infer to be the case in the
world, that there is a cause of
sensation um, that is present uh, when
there is none um, from a quote unquote
objective standpoint. Um, and that's got
to be happening through some combination
of prior and likelihood and uh
differential precisions on on those two
um that give us posterior that is not
consistent with everybody else's
consensual uh hallucination of reality,
if you will. Um, and so we created a
couple of incilical models that uh were
able to generate these kinds of um uh
hallucinations. um and it taught us a
lot about uh the possible implementation
or biologically of what might be going
on when people hallucinate. So the first
model we built was so this is a model
it's a 2018 paper it's a bit old at this
point but it's collective inference and
hallucinations um and the next three
models are all from the same paper um
and this is uh the best we were able to
do in terms of graphical representation
I'm not very good at graphics uh Thomas
Parr who was my co-author here and my
sort of co-supervisor for my my master's
degree um helped a lot with making these
somewhat palatable but they're still a
little bit overwhelming. Um the idea
here was that our states uh are
representing our percept our posterior.
Um whether or not you're hearing
somebody speaking. Um we have outcomes
which are the real outcomes in the world
whether or not you are speaking or and
whether or not you're hearing anybody
else speak. Um and then we have our
policies um where we um um are preparing
ourselves to either listen or to speak
depending on where we think uh we're at
in a in a turntaking conversation. Um
the first thing we found is that agents
hallucinate when um you uh reduce the
sensory precision the zeta uh on the A
matrix sufficiently such that
essentially exterior information no
longer can correct anomalous uh prior
beliefs. The prior beliefs here are
being engendered by the um by the
policies by the sensory expectations of
the policies. So if you expect to be
listening to somebody at the next time
step because you're in a turn taking
conversation you expect the other person
to speak. Um if the person doesn't speak
normally you would correct that
expectation with sensory information. Um
but what what ends up happening is that
uh if you reduce the the precision of
that sensory information um you can no
longer make that correction and then you
actually generate um a a a percept to
fulfill your expectation. So that was
the first piece. Then we did the same
thing uh but now with a slightly
different agent um we modified the um
the gamma. So the prior precision uh
over the um the policies um and gamma as
many of you might know um has been
previously linked to dopamineergic
function uh in work by Schwarzenbeck in
the past. Um and so uh the idea was we
know that dopamine is relevant obviously
in psychosis. how what is the
computational kind of meaning behind
that? And the idea here was that uh in
cases of um uh permissive low sensory
precision, low likelihood precision um
but you had to have the low likelihood
precision um high gamma or an increase
in dopamine was able to kick the agent
over into hallucination. Um so uh but it
only worked if you also had the
reduction in sensory precision.
So dopamine seem to be sort of like
facilitating but not necessarily the the
primary uh mover which makes sense
because patients with schizophrenia
don't lose all of their symptoms when
they're treated with antisycchotics.
They stop hallucinating most of the time
not always but most of the time. Um but
they may they still have a lot of the
other symptoms that come with that. Um
so something about the brain clearly
hasn't changed. It's not all dopamine
dysregulation. Uh there's other pieces
going on here. And to get a sense of
what that might have been, we did a
lesion study which was a lot of fun
because I was, you know, a master
student fresh out of uh medical school
and I'm doing computational lesion
studies and I felt pretty darn cool.
Obviously, this is something many people
do and by no means is unique, but I felt
very fun. I felt very fun doing it. Um,
and so what we did here was that we
built a bunch of uh we built an agent
that had many different policies. Um uh
and one of those policies would lead to
hallucinations. Um we however one the
version A of the agent the unleioned
agent had enough policies enough
flexibility if you will um that if you
uh were to reduce its sensor precision
all the way down to basically zero. It
always had a policy that was correct
that was that was that was consistent
with the world around it and so it
didn't hallucinate. Then you leion that
policy. you you destroy the neurons that
are encoding that those expectations of
the world and now you get hallucinations
because you don't have a um uh you don't
have a prior that is that is that is
non-maladaptive that can rescue your
phenotype. And so we were able to show
that really it was an it was uh there
was an element of lack of sort of
cognitive flexibility of being able to
find solutions um that were not you know
essentially there is a hallucination. uh
when you get rid of all other options
and sensor precision is low uh and you
have maladaptive priors, you get uh you
get hallucinations. And so the
conceptualization that we had here was
maladaptive but strongly held um prior
uh could not be corrected because of
imprecise sensory information which led
to a precise prior belief, imprecise
sensory reference view hallucinations.
This is uh not the only way of thinking
about this even from an active inference
perspective. There's other ways of
thinking about hallucinations that are
are very interesting and we can talk
about if people are interested but this
was the conceptualiz conceptualization
we came to. It was very consistent with
um with patients that I had uh seen in
the hospital. Um I had a patient once
who um you know uh what uh what she
would do was that she would have very
poor sensory precision on essentially
all information. and you would be
talking to her and she was mostly
ignoring you. Um, the environment around
her, she would sort of spend her time
mostly focus focused on what she was
thinking about and not really paying
attention to everything else around her.
Except when there were sirens. Whenever
there were sirens, she was convinced
that the police were coming to get her.
Even though she was already in the
hospital, the police had already come to
get her. It had already happened. She
was convinced they were coming to take
her again. And I looked at her and I
said, "You've already been taken. You're
here. They're not taking you anywhere
else. they already brought you here. Um,
that didn't make a difference to her.
She was convinced. Um, so she was able
to to to allocate sensory precision to
specific kinds of stimuli, but generally
uh was ignoring the rest of the world.
And we're going to talk a little bit
about that when we get to the affective
uh model that I I I alluded to at the
beginning, which is a paper we recently
just published. Well, sorry, it's not
published yet. It's was accepted with
minor revisions at&p. Um, and we're
hoping to get it published relatively
soon. um but it's up as a pre-print that
you can access. Um and we'll talk a
little bit about about where that story
comes into play. So that that one
patient uh and her story has been with
me the entirety of my career at this
point because she's really inspired my
master's work, this most recent paper.
Um I actually saw her uh after my
master's work and I sat down with her. I
said, you know, you inspired my thesis
and I sat down with her and I tried to
go over it with her. Um, I think that
was probably more for me than it was for
her. Um, but it was nice to sort of let
her know that that her story uh sort of
inspired some some academic uh work and
may help other patients in the future.
Anyh who, so this precise prior
imprecise uh evidence view of uh of
hallucinations has had some experimental
validation. Many of you might be
familiar with the landmark study by
Powers at all in 2017 in science that
used the HGF, the hierarchical Gaussian
filter, which which is essentially
simplified active inference. um um and
where they found that uh stronger prior
waiting was in fact um uh the driver
compared to sensory evidence was the
driver of hallucinations in both people
with hallucinations who had psychosis
and people who didn't have psychosis but
had hallucinations kind of like spirit
mediums and and uh and people uh who are
voice hearers but don't have an illness.
So in order to hear hallucinations it is
irrelevant to have an overweighting of
prior compared to sensory
evidence. This didn't really get us much
about the sensory evidence in particular
because it's just a question about
differential waiting, not necessarily
the sensory evidence itself. So I did a
study with with Al who is my mentor now
and I'm very grateful to him um where we
looked at um uh the same task slightly
differently with with a linguistic focus
in a hallucination prone individuals in
a general population sample. In that
sample, we found an interesting thing
which was that patients with
um with um more hallucination proness or
recent hallucinations in the general
population were more likely to require
louder stimuli when establishing their
prior. So a suggestion that perhaps they
uh uh need to be provided more precise
sensory information which which would
suggest that they have lower sensory
precision overall.
Um the priors are also more resistant to
change in uh more versus less
hallucination prone individuals. They
decay slower. So the way the task works
is that you um you condition people to
hallucinate um and uh over time uh you
generate more and more trials where they
will get a condition stimulus that is
supposed to generate the hallucination
but there's no actual auditory stimulus
present. Um, so they hear they see like
a checkerboard. It's like checkerboard
sound, checkerboard sound, checkerboard
sound until they learn that there's a
checkerboard sound association. Then you
show the checkerboard without the sound.
Uh, but you you you present white noise
and they'll hear the sound and the white
noise. Over time, you present more and
more trials where there's the
checkerboard but no sound. So that's
technically evidence against the
association between the checkerboard and
the sound. So you would expect the prior
to decay and it does, but it decays it
decays more slowly in patient in people
with more hallucination proness. um
which suggests either the prior is very
strong and and doesn't decay or that the
sensory information that is being
presented is not sufficient to decay um
that prior. Um so so far we focused
really on the individual patient. Um but
the social environment is key in
psychosis development and often people
in psychosis uh early onset or or
development of psychosis stages um will
have a very poor um uh social bonds.
They will socially isolate and uh
there's sort of a um an overall uh
reduction in in in social contact. Um so
we investigated in a theoretical paper
that I published again with Al how
different kinds of treatments um
programs could impact computational
processes underlying psychotic symptoms.
Why? Because some of the most successful
programs for treatment of psychosis
besides providing medication provide
essentially a uh forced social
interaction because you've got intensive
case management or you've got uh sort of
a very comprehensive program that
involves therapists and doctors and
nurses and you basically are provided
with a group of friends and people um
that uh well not friends obviously
they're your caregivers but they're
they're people that you have uh contact
with um which uh which which we thought
might have an important as an important
uh impact on uh computational mechanisms
of of symptom development and
maintenance. And so we looked at
assertive community treatment which is
basically when you have a team of people
who will like show up at your house
every day or every every couple of days
and they will, you know, make sure you
take your meds and they'll chat with you
and make sure that your uh needs are
taken care of and that you've got a good
uh you know your housing is is is up to
date, your your paying your stuff and
all these things. Um it's a very
effective way of helping these patients.
For those of you who are not familiar
with schizophrenia, that might sound
extraordinarily invasive and
paternalistic, that's probably because
you haven't worked with many people uh
who have uh serious psychotic illness.
Um the reality is because of cognitive
and negative symptoms, people really
need a lot of help. Um and this uh this
help is often uh either much appreciated
or at least very useful for the person.
And then coordinated specialty care
clinics, which is basically like
specialized clinics for people at at
risk for psychosis or who've just
started experiences experiencing
psychosis, which is just a much more
intensive. It's not just see your doctor
every 3 months. You have a case manager,
you have potentially a therapist, a
nurse, um people who you can turn to
when you need help. Um and so when we
thought about this, we wanted to
integrate the social with the the sort
of individual and biological levels. Um
and the idea really was uh that we could
use computational psychiatry as a uh as
a common language to integrate between
these different levels. Um and the idea
was that we could really we could we
could look at this as as sort of a
social treatment. So all these services
are are making sure patients get their
their their medications, but they're
more effective than normal services. And
we we assumed it was more than just
people getting their antisycchotics. Um
and so the idea was you know there could
be different ways in which um the the
access to a more more important social
environment um uh a more active social
environment might help you. So uh one
might be improving sensory precision. So
what do I mean by that? If you have um
you know uh somebody who is coming to
you and giving you good information that
you trust, well maybe you are engaging
with the world a bit better. Maybe you
are artificially boosting the precision
that you're placing on sensory
information which may reduce um cuz we
said the sensory precision is has to be
low for the hall stations to obtain. So
maybe that is helping to reduce your uh
your uh your maladaptive low sensory
precision. Um an expanded policy space
increasing your cognitive flexibility
either through cognitive remediation
like formal therapy or just having
people that you can discuss problems
with and have a sort of extra brains
around you that you can that you can
problem solve with. um that might help
expand your cognitive reserve uh if even
artificially and therefore leave you
less forced to rely on the priors that
uh generate uh hallucinatory uh
behavior. Um there's obviously the
impact of medication which is reducing
the prior precision over policies the
gamma the dopamine so dopamine blockade
um and then um potentially also reducing
the influence of sensory priors. If
you've learned that uh that
hallucination should be present, for
example, um and you have very strong
sensory prior beliefs, um the the the
the help from from therapists or from
from clinicians that you trust over time
to help you realize when those aren't
present uh through things like CBT for
psychosis u might reduce the strength of
those sensory uh prior. So this is an
idea. This is an example of how um the
interaction with the social environment
might actually have an impact on uh the
computational mechanisms underlying um
the uh the development and maintenance
of psychotic
symptoms. Um and then we sort of said
okay fun this is a sort of an idea about
treatment. We have an idea about what
the symptoms are computationally when
they're present. How about um uh symptom
development? So um we had a um uh we
recently published in biological
psychiatry a theory of psychotic symptom
development. Um and so uh here we really
did try and integrate across the
different levels of explanation from the
cellular all the way to the behavioral.
Um and uh the story we came up with was
was this. We know in the beginning of
psychosis that there are changes
neurobbiologically that seem to have an
a strong impact on um cortical
excitability um and just the noise
available in the cortex. Cortex
degenerates and and degrades in many
cases. White matter tracts are not as
integral as they used to be. So
information is less precise in the brain
than it should be. So the idea was
through things like the dis the
hyperunction of NMDA receptors um and uh
and later on dopamine disregulation you
get hyperexitability um and decrease
signal to noise radio in cortex signal
to noise ratio in cortex. Um this leads
to aarent prediction errors. um
inappropriate learning. The
inappropriate learning gives us
delusional formation because um we uh we
we learn uh we learn um uh priors that
that aren't necessarily uh properly
coherent with the evidence because the
learning process has been sort of
poisoned by um by uh by prediction
errors um by aarent prediction errors,
prediction errors that aren't really
based on uh appropriate sensory
information. Um so you start forming
your delusions um and you start
estimating higher environmental
volatility because um you learn over
time uh to that the environment is not
um providing precise information because
it's getting it's it's being f funneled
through a very noisy cortex and so your
impression of that is that the
information itself the the environment
itself isn't precise and so you don't
really know that your own cortex is not
precise precise anymore. Um all over all
of this over time leads to a comp
compensatory increase in prior strength
which um probably is is uh is
computationally manifested at least in
part by dopamineergic dysregulation and
the hyperdopinergic state that we see in
many patients who who develop uh
hallucinations and delusions and then
you get your delusional conviction. So
you actually believe the delusions that
you that you've started to to generate
um and then you generate uh
hallucinations as well with the idea
that the hallucinations probably are a
reaction to the delusion formation. So
you probably have your odd beliefs first
and the hallucinations are generated um
sort of with the delusions as a prior to
those
hallucinations. Um and uh we have
several hypotheses that come from this
directly that we could test with you
know neurobiological and other other
other tests. One of them was that we
expected delusions to emerge before
hallucinations which we actually showed
to be the case in a in a companion paper
to this um from uh three different data
sets. Um hallucinations usually for most
patients emerge after delusions which is
in keeping with at least part of our
model. Um one thing that however isn't
covered in that model is affect um and
the interpersonal aspect. And why is
that important? It's important because
if it was just
noise, there's nothing to say that that
noise should be negatively balanced,
right? If it's just a question of of
apparent prediction errors because of
random cortical noise, well, you you
would expect to have as many positive as
as negative hallucinations, as many
positive as negative delusions. That's
not what we see. What we see is quite
precisely that in patients people with
with with with diagnosed illness you
actually have far more uh negative uhly
veilance hallucinations and delusions
than you do have um positively or
neutally veilance hallucinations or
delusions. Um generally these are
experienced as negative and not just
scary because it's happening but the
content is negative. So it's not like
you're hearing a sound and you're scared
because you're hearing a sound that
isn't there. I mean that does happen but
the the classical descriptions are the
words I'm hearing the voice tell me are
themselves negative. It's telling me
that I'm bad or that I'm useless or
worthless or that I should kill myself
or that uh you know somebody wants to
probe my brain or what have you or that
the NSA is watching me. Um they are or
the in Montreal a common one is that the
mafia is after me because we have a
mafia problem in Montreal. Um it's it's
quite uh specific to the location you're
in.
Um so it the veilance of the experience
itself is negative and so we kind of
built an addition to this model uh that
that that uh uh we we're going to talk
about now. Um which really focused on
the affective component. Um and you know
we looked at previous handling of of
affect and computational psychiatry. Um
we looked at reinforcement learning
drift diffusion modeling active
inference and hierarchal gaussian filter
models. Um active inference actually has
done a lot of work or rather there's a
lot of active inference work especially
by Ryan Smith on uh modeling of um of
affect um probably more than than most
other and more comprehensively than most
other um modeling um approaches though
as often happens in active inference
with less empirical validation which is
sad. Um though Ryan has done a lot of
good work in empirically validating a
lot of his a lot of his
models. Um the idea is that a lot of
these models see a effective states um
as uh a dynamic modulation of current
and future expectations intimately
linked with interception uh and
individual differences in emotional
awareness and to be both state and
traitlike. So you can feel a certain way
in the moment and also have a mood over
a longer time.
Um there wasn't as much of a of a focus
however on how affect and and and social
uh interactions interact and we know you
know from anybody who's spoken to other
human beings um interactions other
people certainly has an effect on our
mood. My apologies.
Um so we actually built a a new version
of our of our model. Uh it has every all
the pieces that we talked about
previously. Um but essentially we added
uh an affective component. So in our new
conceptualization
um you have as we talked about
degradation of cortical neural signals
and increased expected sensory noise um
which not only provides the the the soup
in which you can develop delusions and
and hallucinations and that is
permissive to those but also directly
affects affective states which makes
sense because if you think about papers
like um the affective papers by by Smith
and Hesp um you know uh having uh
knowing that one's model of the world is
imprecise
um is going to lead to a negative
effective outcome because we would like
to have precise models of the world. If
we find ourselves in a state in which
our model of the world is not precise
because we are not because our our
cortical machinery is not precise. So
we're not able to integrate sensory
information very very effectively. We're
going to notice this and we're going to
have negative out a effect as a as a
result. Um the um other idea we had was
that and this is the disconnection
hypothesis that that Carl has written a
lot about. Um we know that there's
degradation of connections between
temporal uh and frontal regions.
Generally speaking when that happens
because a lot of the the emotional stuff
is in the temporal lobe uh and it's
being uh regulated by the the frontal
lobe. um if you don't have effective
connectivity between those regions um
there may be sort of um an overabundance
of of negative a effect. So we have a
negative affective state. This negative
act effective state actually uh then
does exactly what affect has been shown
to do in many other computational
modeling approaches. Um it will bias
your expectations of the future which
makes sense. If we expect bad things to
happen, we will take actions that will
align with that expectation to protect
ourselves. Um so our expectations our
priors become more and more negative
over time. Normally we would have our
observations to rescue this. So if you
know we we have a bad day where we're
not somebody who who has psychosis, we
have a bad day um we should be able to
over the next couple of days if good
things happen kind of recalibrate our
expectations of the future. But if our
if our if our our likelihood precision
is low and we can't use information uh
effectively, we may not be able to
recalibrate as effectively. In addition,
um, affect has been shown to to to to
modify how we explore the environment.
Um, and the idea here being that we are
probably going to be negatively biasing
our exploration. Um, we're going to be
uh expecting negative outcomes. We will
be looking out for negative outcomes
because they're generally worse for us
than positive outcomes are good for us.
Right? If there's a line in the forest,
that's more important not to miss than a
cookie on the ground. Um, and so we're
going to be biased also towards uh
negative uh interpretations of the world
and and and and exploring negative
outcomes and ignoring the positive ones.
Um this leads to a more and more and
more negative uh posterior um which uh
affects our long-term beliefs because if
we keep in the moment experiencing
negative uh beliefs about what's going
on that's going to change our longunning
priors um which uh over time might cause
us to socially isolate um and eventually
become the priors that lead to um
hallucinations and delusions. And this
is
why patients have specifically
negatively veilance hallucinations and
delusions. Interestingly, in people who
are healthy voice hearers, you don't get
a lot of negative affect and often their
hallucinations and delusions are much
more positive or they're more spiritual.
They're not they're not they're not
disabling because they're not associated
or not as dis obviously some people
still struggle but they're not they're
cl they're not clinical people by
definition. So generally speaking,
they're functional and they have, you
know, much more positive or and healthy
in in many cases relationships with
their with their experiences. And so one
hypothesis for why this might be would
be that they don't have the the cortical
degeneration that leads to the negative
affect that leads to the specifically
negatively violent veilance uh priors
over time. um and why they can go about
their lives being you know spirit
mediums or what have you and living
normal happy fulfilling lives and people
with schizophrenia uh not so much uh
when it comes to their hallucinations
and delusions um so it's not the
hallucination itself that becomes the
focus it's really the effective and and
functional outcomes which is I think a
much more humane way of approaching it I
don't I tell patients this all the times
if they come to me and they have a
hallucination and they don't doesn't
bother them and they don't care and
doesn't affect their daily life or they
have a positive association with it. I
don't really care. Doesn't really bother
me. I treat symptoms. That's not a
symptom in my opinion. Right. I have a
patient actually who has schizophrenia,
a very mild case, but she's she's doing
very well. Um, we treated her for her
very negative hallucinations and over
time she had one voice left that became
a positive voice. She was able to shift
it into a a positive kind of friend that
she can bounce ideas off of and that
doesn't bother her when she doesn't want
it to bother her. And I looked at her
and I said, "I mean, if you want, we can
keep increasing the dose of your
medication until it's gone, but I don't
know if we need to, if your life is fine
right now." And she said, "Honestly, I'm
okay with it." And we left it. And she's
fine and happy with with that voice
remaining. Um, she's very open about it,
talks about it. Um, and uh, and it
doesn't for me, it's not a symptom if
it's not if it's not causing her
distress, right? And I think it's
because we were able to help her change
her affective uh view of the symptoms um
her experience of those symptoms and her
brain also I think was more intact than
most patients uh and she was able and we
also treated her very quickly um and she
was we were able to to make that change
um and she she's having a better outcome
because of it.
Um so in summary uh computational
psychiatry can be used uh to integrate
across multiple levels of explanation.
Um we can link the social
neurobiological and individual levels of
explanation. Uh the core next up of
course is empirical validation
development of novel treatments based on
all of this. Um and um uh we have the
two recent reviews that are both up and
and available to read. um in those we
have generated very specific model
predictions for empirical validation. So
um both from a computational standpoint
but also phenomenologically like we
actually say for example if this model
is true we expect that you know if you
treat patients who are at risk for
psychosis for their negative effect
during the risk period we don't
necessarily expect that to stop
transition to psychosis but we expect
the intensity and the negativity of the
psychotic phenomena to be less negative
and less intense when psychosis does
onset. Um so that's a very specific re
prediction. Um uh that is probably uh
only true if the affect really has a
something to do with the the veilance of
the uh of the priors which drive the
hallucinations afterwards. Um we're also
working on an a effect a version of the
conditional hallucinations task uh the
one that Dr. Powers developed that I
talked about before. Um and the results
so far seem to be consistent with the
idea that um you know uh uh prior
beliefs uh about negative things are
kind of privileged in patient
populations compared to prior beliefs
about negative things um and will lead
to more hallucinations and and higher
prior
waiting. Um and that my friends is uh is
that um before we finish up and and and
ask uh people to ask questions um I try
to keep it to 45 minutes so that we have
time for questions. Um I'd like to
invite everybody who's here um to the
6th International Workshop on active
inference October 15th to 17th in
Montreal Canada where I am. Um it is the
first time that this conference is
happening in North America. Um so all of
those of you from North America, please
come. Um uh it will be uh it will be
lovely to have you. Um and uh it's a you
know premier conference on active
inference of course. We'll be having a
lot of great speakers. Carl will be
there in person. So if you want to meet
Carl in person, this is your chance. He
doesn't get out often uh much uh anymore
uh by his own admission. So if you want
to meet Carl in person, come. But we'll
also be having Ryan Smith, Chris
Matthysse, and a number of other
wonderful speakers um on the Beijian
brain and active inference who'll be
present. Um I am one of the co-chairs of
the conference. I uh we we we put in a
bid for Montreal. We won. Um which is
great but also terrifying because we
have to fill the seats. So please
register. Early bird is still available
until the 28th. Uh we we extended the
early bird period. So, if you go on the
website, you don't see the early bird
extension, it's fine. The links work.
Uh, you can buy your tickets up until
next week. Um, so, uh, please get them
because the price does go up afterwards.
Um, and, uh, we'd love to see you in
Montreal. Um, the call for submissions
is still open. You can submit extended
abstracts or full papers as you wish.
Um, and we expect that the majority of
of of applica of submissions, if they're
not selected for talks, will at least be
selected for an abstract. We can't
commit, we can't promise that obviously
if somebody produced something that our
peer reviewers do not like then it won't
get in but most things will at least be
an abstract. So please do um submit and
we look forward to seeing you in
Montreal. Um and the website is just if
you if you Google IY
IWI 2025 you will find it. Um it's it's
a GitHub website.
Um that's it.
Awesome. Thank you. Questions? Great.
Yes, those in the live chat. Please feel
free to write more questions and I will
just read them from the top.
Okay. Andrew P writes, "Very exciting.
Thank you for the presentation. Always
on the search for measurable substrates
here. You briefly mention the
relationship between gamma and
dopamineergic activity. I've been
fascinated by the prospect of aligning
model components with
neurotransmissions. The active inference
paradol textbook 2022 provides a table
on some potential evidence for
likelihood precision being more
relatable to acetylcholine or serotonin
for interosceptive likelihood. Any
thoughts on this or other
neurotransmitter cognitive
relationships?
Yeah, for sure. So I think um uh the the
two big ones we often talk about right
are I guess three if you count the
serotonin for the interception um are
the um dopamine for for prior precision
and the
um uh acetylcholine for attention and
and likelihood precision uh likelihood
precision by means of attention
essentially it's how you manipulate
attention um and so you can deploy it in
different places. And what's really fun
about that is that you could
theoretically deploy it differentially.
So you could have uh deployment of
attention to specific stimula but not
others. Um which is relevant because we
can we can or orthogonalize things in
active inference. So it's nice in that
way. Um so I think those are the big
ones. I think there is some empirical
validation for the dopamine one. The
acetylon is I think a little bit more uh
theoretical in nature. Um but uh but
that is the the story. And I I think
it's interesting when you think about
the fact that um you know in some of the
dementias we have acetylcholine uh
reduction um and you have uh
hallucinations and delusions um that are
often a bit different than you get in
psychosis. There there's similarities
but also differences um uh you know uh
that that might be lead to them being
more sort of likelihood driven than
prior driven um at least in in certain
cases. Um the
um other interesting thing is is is as I
mentioned the uh
zunomaleneium the new antisycchotic is
actually a procolonergic
uh antisycchotic uh and it's also the uh
the only other really significantly
procolic antisycchotic least that that I
use commonly is clausipine which is the
best antisycotic um which has a bit of
uh colonergic agonist effect um and that
may be why it's so good we don't
Clausify is a very dirty drug. It it
basically touches every receptor. So we
don't really know why it works, but it
works. Um and so I think uh it's
important to do more empirical studies.
Pet studies would be good uh for this
kind of thing. Um but that requires you
know money and expertise in in that in
those um methodologies. what's really
relevant um is making sure that one does
not get too wrapped up in just the
neurotransmitter story. So one idea that
we've had in the past was there is
probably a component that is
neurotransmitter and a component that is
structural right or that is circuit
based. So, um, that's why, you know, if
you don't get full resolution of your
symptoms with a neurotransmitter change,
don't get too sad, but it's cuz it's
probably because there's also, uh, a
structural effect on the circuit as
well. Um, and so, uh, you may need to
think about decomposing your
computational terms into a
neurotransmitter sensitive, a
neurotransmitter insensitive term. Like
for example for for likelihood precision
you could have the acetal colon
responsible for a certain percentage of
that and then the um uh sort of white
matter white matter attractor or gray
matter generation responsible for
another percentage of that um uh and the
sort of other component that I think is
relevant to that would be um uh I lost
my train I thought it's fine continue
next question
great yeah that speaks like partitioning
variance across different levels of
analysis, different
subsystems, and taking the total
overall cognitive or phenotypic variance
and then looking at how certain parts
have like additive or interactive
effects as we get different measurements
across different levels. But like that
came up in for example insect research
because for a fruitfly the affinities
for a given drug might be known or there
might even be designer drugs or
transgenic lines whereas for most
insects the affinities for different
pharmaceuticals to the receptors it's
just not even known. So then it's like,
well then how do you um think about what
the effects are when there's these
uncertainties around affinities? But
even if you knew the affinities
perfectly, it's like there's like
secondary signaling. So so many parts
and yet those are intervention points
empirically that actually do very
naturally and open themselves up to
causal intervention. So it's like not
hopeless but it has this whole
biological complexity which is why
having the interoperable generative
models where you can actually talk about
mixing and blending uh across those
levels that's like kind of why those
model formats matter. Yes, I agree.
Okay, another question from Andrew who
wrote, "Does a notion of trust come up
in your research? GG for understanding
or treating
psychosis. I suppose it does implicitly
if the patient is unsure if they can
trust sensory stimuli but I suppose in a
social
sense. Yeah. So I think it depends at
what level cuz the other point right is
that I'm presenting these parameters as
if they were singular things but really
they're played out over hierarchies in
the brain right um and just because of
time and also the complexity I I kind
of pretended they were singular things
but they're not um so yes trust does
certainly play a role at the sort of
almost metacognitive level of what is it
that I'm thinking about Right? And where
where can I place my trust in not but
the sensory precision story goes all the
way down to sort of the very basic like
intactness of information right so
there's a low precision on information
because of low confidence at a very low
level and then there's higher level low
confidence uh probably that's been
that's been uh shaped over time by that
lower level lack of confidence. Um but
uh but I think yes for sure trust does
does play a role. Many patients are very
untrusting um when they're especially
when they're acutely psychotic. Um
usually because they've they've seem to
have learned that the environment is not
trustworthy and the only thing they can
resolve uncertainty with is their own
prior beliefs. Um which clearly makes it
difficult to have a a trusting
conversation. You have to build that
over time. sort of gently introduce uh a
bit more precision into the hierarchy
until they see you as a precise source
of uh information.
Yeah, that reminds me of the kind of
work like in altered states of
consciousness and mapping out spaces
where it's like I'm sure I'm seeing this
rare animal or like I'm surprised I'm
seeing this common thing or I'm not
certain but it's familiar. So there's
all these different
intersecting precisions and and beliefs
about beliefs which is kind of why again
like the cognitive model um is is
important to to have and to build
variance of. And another part I thought
was really interesting about the models
was uh there was a part about the policy
precision.
So that would and also I think adding or
changing the affordance space or the
policy space. So just interesting that
that um there could be
different steps or parts in the system
like the sensory precision or signal
might be a um
peripheral pathology or damage or just
variation. But that is a totally
different uh situation than
uh memory mediated changes in belief.
And then all of that is again kind of
factorized off from well what is done
about it. Yeah. What what is in the the
person's or whatever the systems uh
what's the probability distribution of
their action outputs
and so certain things depending on
sensitivities that that could be
exaggerated or um even like take a a
counter seeming response. So then I
think that is like the challenge that
you brought up at the beginning. Well,
what space is optimal about that? Mhm.
But that that's how that whole space is
mapped.
Yes. Under that
toddloical assumption like well whatever
it is that will be the base optimal for
what it is. But what is it? Right.
Right. Yeah. Exactly. For sure.
Um is there anything you're like wanting
to add about where you're going to take
it or anything else you want to say
about IY?
Uh I mean I guess
the in terms of where we want to take it
uh the what we really want to do is
longitudinal studies of uh you know we
have all these ideas of of the different
parameters that are going to be
influenced at different stages and and
and how they're reacting with each other
longitudinal longitudinally through time
right this whole longitudinal aspect is
something that is and you know obviously
discussed but um we don't really have
good aside from a couple by Ryan Smith
longitudinal studies of computational
parameters in patients. Um it's just not
something that we've done because you
know you need money for that and uh our
field uh has been able to do really
really cool cross-sectional studies and
a couple of sort of longitudinal studies
but not so many kind of like large
cohort studies over time. Um, and what
we really want to do is we want to we
we've built a battery of these tasks.
Um, in fact, if anybody's interested in
in in using a battery of of of these
tasks, um, we're looking for beta
testers. Uh, if you're interested um to
to we we had a small grant from Miguel
to build a computational battery. Uh,
it's readyish for testing. We're just
fixing a couple of last bugs. Uh,
there's four different tasks that are in
there. Uh, a fifth one is on its way and
then we're going to be adding in all the
modeling as well. and you got everything
for all the outputs. Um, and so the idea
would be
to use this battery which measures
different parameters sorry in um in
tasks across time in different
populations uh with different risk
profiles uh for psychosis um to see if
we're actually right about the sequence
of onset the sequence of events that we
that we are describing. uh because it
would be really nice to be able to say
yes in fact we do see an increase in
sensory noise over time and we do then
see after a lag period prior is
increasing and after a lag period uh
expected environmental volatility is
increasing and and it's it's matching up
with uh with what we expect. Um so we've
been trying to get that funded for the
last year and a half. Uh it has not yet
succeeded but we are working on it. We
were funded at least to turn some of
these tasks into a proper video game.
That was fun. So, we're going to be
working on developing a a computational
video game uh of of tasks that kind of
uh like for example, you can turn the
conditionalist nations task into a
avoiding a dragon. Um which is kind of
fun. Um but anyways, um the uh I think
the future really is in getting good
longitudinal data and making sure that
it what we have really does map onto how
symptoms evolve over time. Um and then
with that the neurobiological validation
um uh in subsamples of those samples. Uh
so that that's the future work assuming
that someone gives us money to do it. If
anybody out there is a funer who uh is
listening in on this uh and has you a
couple million extra bucks that they got
to spend before the end of the year, hit
me up. I'm ready to spend it. Um and if
not uh please do come to join us at uh
at IY. It'll be a lot of fun to see all
of you guys uh that I can't see right
now. Um and uh and we're going to have a
really really really good conference
this year. Go seriously go check out the
website. It's a fantastic lineup. Uh and
I think uh I would just love to see uh
many registrations after today. And
remember early bird ends next week. So
go get your
tickets. You can register and then
submit your paper later if you want. But
register we need to we need to know that
we have enough butts and seats to fill
the space.
Good. Okay, cool. That's all for me.
Thank you. Well, thank you for the
presentation and for joining also
wishing you the best for IY. So, till
next time. Bye. Thank you. Take care.